What did the first smear FRAME EVER LOOK
LIKE? IF YOU don't know, a smear frame
is a technique used by animators to
highlight and exaggerate fast motion in
order to keep the movements clearly
readable. They usually only appear for
one frame or a fraction of a second, but
they're super fun to just pause on and
admire. How do I look? There's instances
of smear frames in almost every cartoon
made today. The Simpsons is famous for
them. My footnotes have them. Even
Family Guy has a few in modern 3D
movies. We're starting to see more and
more 2D inspired smears as well. Thank
you, Spiderverse.
>> You're welcome.
>> And hell, even Stopotion's got them,
too. Why not? But, okay. Okay, we got
it.
But when was the first smear frame? What
did it look like?
This here is probably what many people
would consider to be the first
appearance of a smear frame, but it's
not. This is from an old Warner Brothers
cartoon called The Dover Boys at Pimento
University and it was released in 1942.
This cartoon is credited for having the
first major use of smear frames because
it was very liberal with them and it was
very popular. But I already knew that
Wikipedia was wrong on this one cuz
check this out. Huh. 1941 from Porky's
Pooch. Oh, 1936.
Popeye. Look at that smear. Oh, 1933.
Another one 10 years before the supposed
first occurrence of smear frames. We got
a pretty one here from Battling Bosow in
1932. And that's the earliest example I
could find anyone talking about online.
So, I took it upon myself to scrutinize
a bunch of even older cartoons frame by
frame. I found an old Felix the Cat
short FROM ALL THE WAY BACK in 1923,
over 100 years ago, called Felix Gets
Broadcasted, and it has this fun little
smear. But 3 years before that, we have
Mut and Jeff in Fishing from 1920 with
some real early smears. But they even
had themselves beat one year prior with
this smear in Mut and Jeff Playing with
Fire in 1919. And I thought this one had
to be the first cuz there was already
almost no smearing in animation in the
1920s, let alone the 1910s. But then I
found this little gem called Gertie the
Dinosaur from way back in 1914.
basically prehistoric in the animation
world. This tune was made for part of a
vaudeville circus act of all things. And
it's the first animated film to ever
feature a dinosaur. And you can spot
this super rare ancient smear frame when
she picks up this rock. So that must be
the oldest one. Not cuz then I found an
even older smear. Yes, I do. This is
called How a Mosquito Operates and it's
from 1912. It's an earlier piece from
Windsor McKay, the creator of Gertie the
Dinosaur. And this is one of the oldest
works of animation. Yet, it's still
considered way ahead of its time due to
its high technical complexity. And it
also contains the oldest examples of
animation smearing here, here, and here.